<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Philipp Garbe´s Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://pgarbe.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pgarbe.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-08T12:20:43+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pgarbe.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philipp Garbe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://pgarbe.github.io/blog/2014/01/08/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T09:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pgarbe.github.io/blog/2014/01/08/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is a nice <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hello_world_program">tradition</a> to start with a &ldquo;Hello world&rdquo; program when you learn a new programming language . Although this is my first blog post, it feels also like learning a new programming language. It also helps me to get in touch with <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> and <a href="http://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages</a> where this blog is hosted. I also need to get more familiar with markdown.</p>

<p>Let me tell you some details about myself. My name is Philipp Garbe and I started programming when I was a teen (Some C++ but mostly VB). After .Net was first-time released I switched to C# and it is still my favourite language. But in the last couple of months I came more and more in contact with Ruby and F#. And not to forget my love-hate relationship with JavaScript. For almost all of my projects I use Git as version control and the more I work with it the more I like it. It´s not that easy at the beginning (compared to subverion) but it has a lot of power.</p>

<p>Since several years now, I work for a great <a href="http://www.autoscout24.de">company</a> in Munich. We work in very agile teams and I have the freedom to experiment with techniques like CQRS, Event Sourcing and DDD. I also believe that  <a href="http://continuousdelivery.com/">Continous Delivery</a> (or <a href="http://continuousdelivery.com/2010/08/continuous-delivery-vs-continuous-deployment/">Continous Deployment</a> if possible) is fundamental for good teams and good products.</p>

<p>So, what´s next? There will be some interesting news in the next weeks. Together with my colleague <a href="http://www.matthias-kainer.de">Matthias</a> I started a new project that should make releases less painful. I don´t want to spoiler so <a href="http://pgarbe.github.io/atom.xml">subscribe</a> to this blog and you´ll be updated.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
